<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Śikha Pariṣad - An initiative by Sri Kanchi Kamakoti Peetam on Śikha Parisad</title><link>https://sikhaparisad.org/</link><description>Recent content in Śikha Pariṣad - An initiative by Sri Kanchi Kamakoti Peetam on Śikha Parisad</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://sikhaparisad.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Chaula Karma</title><link>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/chaulakarma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/chaulakarma/</guid><description>Chaula Karma is a samskaram performed at an early age of a boy. Both Mother and Father of the boy get involved in performing this karma. This article documents the procedure that should be followed during this karma along with the mantras to be chanted by the father.
Before start of the karma, the boy should sit facing east and the mother should sit behind the boy. Father should stand facing north.</description></item><item><title>Pancha Sikha</title><link>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/panchasikha/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/panchasikha/</guid><description>Pañca Śikha is a samskaram performed at the time of upanayanam. This is done before the yagnopaveetha daaranam. During this karma, the boys is head gets shaved except at five spots. These spots signify the four directions (East, West, North, and South) and the top spot represents the adhipati marma.
Note: The mantras for each direction are same as what is described in Chaula Karma.
Before the shave, warm water is to be smeared on the head, with the recitation of the mantra “ऊष्णेन वाय उदकेनेहि । अदिति: केशान् वपतु”.</description></item><item><title>Gallery</title><link>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/gallery/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/gallery/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;d like your photos featured here in this gallery, contact ravikanth @ ravichaganti dot com.</description></item><item><title>Śikha Vandanam</title><link>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/vandanam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sikhaparisad.org/docs/sikha/vandanam/</guid><description>For all nitya and naimithika karma observation, it is mandatory that the Śikha must be tied as a knot. Samavarta Smriti mentions, a twice-born (a dwija) who stands without washing his feet, or who performs the achamanam without binding the tuft of his hair (Śikha) on the crown or without putting on his sacred thread, is impure.
Sikhodhakam Water squeezed out of a man’s upper cloth and water let down in from from the tip of the śikha alone reach in the form of tarpanam to our forefathers.</description></item></channel></rss>